Guide to the F. W. Heitmann Company business ledgers, 1873-1959 MS 070
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
F.W. Heitmann Company business ledgers
1873-1959
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
F.W. Heitmann Company.
MS 070
53 Linear Feet
The F. W. Heitmann Company business ledgers contains business materials from the F. W. Heitmann Company. It includes assorted business information and records, including daybooks, journals, monthly reports, business ledgers, account books, registers, balance sheets, invoices, inventories, catalogs, city sales records, and lists of shipments received. Most of the collection is still in its original bindings, in large ledgers. Much of the information is hand-written.
Biographical Note
Frederick William Heitmann was born in Potsdam, Germany, in 1828, but lived most of his life in Houston, Texas, as did his wife Mary Mathilde (Erhard). In 1865, Mr. Heitmann opened a heavy metal and hardware store in Houston, Texas, at 113 Main Street, where it stayed for 81 years. Mr. Heitmann died in 1889. In the early 1870s, Mr. H.S. Fox, then president of the Houston National Bank, became a partner in Houston's oldest hardware store and its name changed to Fox and Heitmann. In 1903 the firm was incorporated under the name F.W. Heitmann and Company.. At that time the founder's son, Frederick A. Heitmann became president of the company. Originally hardware establishment, the firm soon became a major post-Civil War importer of all lines of heavy hardware, tools, bar iron, tin plates, etc. from England and Germany. As the company grew it added major lines of domestically manufactured heavy machinery and became a major provider of products for rice growing and cotton ginning in the Southwest. It also furnished heavy equipment to the railroads and to the city of Houston.
Scope and Contents
The collection is primarily composed of large bound volumes dating from 1873 to 1959. It also contains some papers removed from their binding and stored in folders and boxes. It contains daybooks, journals, monthly reports, business ledgers, account books, registers, balance sheets, invoices, inventories, catalogs, city sales records, and lists of shipments received.
Access Restrictions
This material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the Harris County Heritage Society, 2005.
Index Terms
Subjects
Business
Document Types
reports; daybooks; journals (accounts)
- Series I: Daybooks/Journals/Monthly Reports, 1874-1958, 257883
  - Daybook 1874-1876, 257896 (Box 1)
  - Daybook 1876-1878, 257895 (Box 2)
  - Daybook 1878-1879, 257894 (Box 3)
  - Daybook 1881-1883, 257893 (Box 4)
  - Daybook 1883-1885, 257892 (Box 5)
  - Daybook (sales) 1887-1888, 257891 (Box 6)
  - Daybook 1889, 257890 (Box 6)
  - Journal 1892-1894, 257889 (Box 7)
  - Journal 1894-1896, 257888 (Box 8)
  - [Bering-Cortes Hardware Co.] Journal 1954-1956, 257887 (Box 9)
  - [Bering-Cortes Hardware Co.] Journal 1956-1958, 257886 (Box 10)
  - [Bering-Cortes Hardware Co.] Monthly Report 1943-1954, 257885 (Box 11)
  - [Bering-Cortes Hardware Co.] Monthly Report 1954-1958, 257884 (Box 11)
- Series II: Ledgers, 1873-1913, 257868
  - Ledger 1873-1876, 257882 (Box 12)
  - Ledger 1876-1878, 257881 (Box 13)
  - Ledger 1878-1880, 257880 (Box 14)
  - Ledger 1887, 257879 (Box 15)
  - Ledger 1899-1902, 257878 (Box 16)
  - Ledger 1902-1908, 257877 (Box 17)
  - Ledger 1908-1913, 257876 (Box 18)
  - Ledger 1913-1917, 257875 (Box 19)
  - Ledger 1917-1921, 257874 (Box 20)
  - Ledger 1921-1925, 257873 (Box 21)
  - Private Ledger 1925-1929, 257872 (Box 22)
  - Private Ledger 1929-1933, 257871 (Box 23)
  - Purchase Ledger 1904-1909, 257870 (Box 24)
  - Purchase Ledger 1909-1913, 257869 (Box 25)
- Series III: Account Books/Registers/Catalogs/Invoices, 1881-1957, 257854
  - Account Book 1881-1885, 257867 (Box 26)
  - Account Book 1887-1888, 257866 (Box 27)
  - Alphabetical Account Book 1896, 257865 (Box 27)
  - Cash Accounts 1878-1885, 257864 (Box 28)
  - Check Register 1954-1957, 257863 (Box 29)
  - Voucher Register 1956, 257862 (Box 30)
  - Invoices 1899, 257861 (Box 31)
  - Catalog; one of two, 257860 (Box 32)
  - Catalog; two of two, 257859 (Box 33)
  - Catalog: Draft, 257858 (Box 34)
  - Cash Accounts 1885-1891, 257857 (Box 35)
  - Ledger 1885-1887, 257856 (Box 36)
  - Ledger 1900-1903, 257855 (Box 37)
- Series IV: Inventory/Account Books/Balance Sheets/Registers/City Sales Record/Shipments Received, 1949-1958, 257833
  - Account Book 1903, 257853 (Box 38, Folder 1)
  - Account Book (Profit and Loss) 1909-1917, 257852 (Box 38, Folder 2)
  - Alphabetical Account Book, 257851 (Box 38, Folder 3)
  - Balance Sheets, 257850 (Box 38, Folder 4)
  - Inventory 1952, 257849 (Box 38, Folder 5)
  - Inventory 1952-1953, 257848 (Box 38, Folder 6)
  - Commerce Ave. Warehouse Inventory c. 1949; folder 1 of 4, 257847 (Box 38, Folder 7)
  - Commerce Ave. Warehouse Inventory c. 1949; folder 2 of 4, 257846 (Box 39, Folder 1)
  - Commerce Ave. Warehouse Inventory c. 1949; folder 3 of 4, 257845 (Box 39, Folder 2)
  - Commerce Ave. Warehouse Inventory c. 1949; folder 4 of 4, 257844 (Box 39, Folder 3)
  - North Main Warehouse Inventory 1949; folder 1 of 2, 257843 (Box 39, Folder 4)
  - North Main Warehouse Inventory 1949; folder 2 of 2, 257842 (Box 39, Folder 5)
  - Belting Book 1901-1909, 257841 (Box 40, Folder 1)
  - City Sales Records #34, 257840 (Box 40, Folder 2)
  - City Sales Records #50, #53, #54, 257839 (Box 40, Folder 3)
  - City Sales Records #56, 257838 (Box 40, Folder 4)
  - Shipments Received 1958; folder 1 of 2, 257837 (Box 40, Folder 5)
  - Shipments Received 1958; folder 2 of 2, 257836 (Box 40, Folder 6)
  - Cash Receipts 1958-1959, 257835 (Box 41, Folder 1)
  - City Register 1953-1954, 257834 (Box 41, Folder 2)
- Series V: Addendum
  - F.W. Heitmann & Co., Houston, Texas. Catalogue no. 99, n.d. (Box 42)